<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Projects | Geert Litjens</title><link>https://geertlitjens.nl/project/</link><atom:link href="https://geertlitjens.nl/project/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>Projects</description><generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2019</copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 11 Jan 2022 15:32:00 +0100</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://geertlitjens.nl/media/icon_hue0c2058e8f722cf54419e3dfd4f45926_15543_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url><title>Projects</title><link>https://geertlitjens.nl/project/</link></image><item><title>Eu Pancaim</title><link>https://geertlitjens.nl/project/eu-pancaim/</link><pubDate>Tue, 11 Jan 2022 15:32:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://geertlitjens.nl/project/eu-pancaim/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Imi Bigpicture</title><link>https://geertlitjens.nl/project/imi-bigpicture/</link><pubDate>Tue, 11 Jan 2022 15:31:52 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://geertlitjens.nl/project/imi-bigpicture/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Vidi Icarus</title><link>https://geertlitjens.nl/project/vidi-icarus/</link><pubDate>Tue, 11 Jan 2022 15:29:56 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://geertlitjens.nl/project/vidi-icarus/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Erc Aiscap</title><link>https://geertlitjens.nl/project/erc-aiscap/</link><pubDate>Tue, 11 Jan 2022 15:29:38 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://geertlitjens.nl/project/erc-aiscap/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Ppp Deepgrading</title><link>https://geertlitjens.nl/project/ppp-deepgrading/</link><pubDate>Tue, 11 Jan 2022 15:29:21 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://geertlitjens.nl/project/ppp-deepgrading/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Automated Analysis of Histopathological Clinical Trial Data</title><link>https://geertlitjens.nl/project/aahctd/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Apr 2015 12:16:34 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://geertlitjens.nl/project/aahctd/</guid><description>&lt;p>To accuractely determine the outcome of clinical trials careful analysis of the biomarkers is required. In recent years this has become more and more complex due to quantity of biomarkers that has to be assessed in new clinical trials. Furthermore, as we move to more personalized therapy, we need to be able to measure even subtle changes in biomarker expression, putting a larger emphasis on accurate and precise biomarker quantification. These changes have made manual assessment of biomarker expression tedious, time-consuming, and, often, inaccurate.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure id="figure-quantification-of-cd3-positive-cells-inside-yellow-and-outside-green-the-invasive-margin-of-prostate-cancer-orange-specimens">
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="Quantification of CD3-positive cells inside (yellow) and outside (green) the invasive margin of prostate cancer (orange) specimens." srcset="
/project/aahctd/featured_hu8dea62950b20b086faff196c1d701874_176128_b9d45b7c0672b0f780191e26c3615847.webp 400w,
/project/aahctd/featured_hu8dea62950b20b086faff196c1d701874_176128_9cf9f7d9074c024bb7cc885154553a61.webp 760w,
/project/aahctd/featured_hu8dea62950b20b086faff196c1d701874_176128_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w"
src="https://geertlitjens.nl/project/aahctd/featured_hu8dea62950b20b086faff196c1d701874_176128_b9d45b7c0672b0f780191e26c3615847.webp"
width="50%"
height="484"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;figcaption>
Quantification of CD3-positive cells inside (yellow) and outside (green) the invasive margin of prostate cancer (orange) specimens.
&lt;/figcaption>&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Within this project, funded by the &lt;a href="https://www.humboldt-foundation.de/web/home.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Humboldt Foundation&lt;/a>, we set out to develop machine learning tools to automate the quantification and discovery of biomarkers in a variety of clinical trials. Specifically, we looked at applications in prostate cancer immunotherapy, lung cancer prognosis, and MAGE-expression in head and neck cancers.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>ASAP</title><link>https://geertlitjens.nl/project/asap/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2014 12:25:34 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://geertlitjens.nl/project/asap/</guid><description>&lt;p>ASAP (Automated Slide Analysis Platform) was developed by the Computation Pathology Group, part of the Diagnostic Image Analysis Group, at the Radboud University Medical Center. It was started after frustration with the current freely available software for annotating multi-resolution digital pathology images. For more details head to the project site.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Computerized Detection of Prostate Cancer in Multi-Parametric MRI</title><link>https://geertlitjens.nl/project/mpmri-pca/</link><pubDate>Thu, 07 Jan 2010 11:55:45 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://geertlitjens.nl/project/mpmri-pca/</guid><description>&lt;p>Prostate cancer is the most commonly diagnosed malignancy and the second leading cause of cancer death among men in the Netherlands. Due to the shortcomings of the current diagnostic pathway for prostate cancer, especially with respect to assessing cancer aggressiveness, alternative strategies are being investigated. Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) has emerged as an important modality to assist and potentially replace (part of) the current diagnostic pathway. The high complexity of prostate MRI and the lack of sufficient expertise among the radiological community at large has opened the door for (semi-)automated analysis of prostate MRI by computer systems, with or without human intervention.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure id="figure-transversal-slide-through-the-prosate-in-a-t2-weighted-mri-sequence">
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="Transversal slide through the prosate in a T2-weighted MRI sequence." srcset="
/project/mpmri-pca/featured_hu82c705709ed6cbe2deb511e0b8d9074a_253218_2b4c3d61f6cf40e2e403ae0e13e40869.webp 400w,
/project/mpmri-pca/featured_hu82c705709ed6cbe2deb511e0b8d9074a_253218_d4b4077858c208b27c05cd8b85eabe35.webp 760w,
/project/mpmri-pca/featured_hu82c705709ed6cbe2deb511e0b8d9074a_253218_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w"
src="https://geertlitjens.nl/project/mpmri-pca/featured_hu82c705709ed6cbe2deb511e0b8d9074a_253218_2b4c3d61f6cf40e2e403ae0e13e40869.webp"
width="50%"
height="545"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;figcaption>
Transversal slide through the prosate in a T2-weighted MRI sequence.
&lt;/figcaption>&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Within this project such as system was developed and evaluated. It consisted of several key components: segmentation of the prostate gland in MRI, discovering cancer-specific features, system development and evaluation. The results were reported through a number of publications which are listed below and summarized in my &lt;a href="https://geertlitjens.nl/publication/litj-15-a/">PhD Thesis&lt;/a>.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>CAMELYON</title><link>https://geertlitjens.nl/project/camelyon/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://geertlitjens.nl/project/camelyon/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="overview">Overview&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Built on the success of its predecessor, CAMELYON17 is the second grand challenge in pathology organised by the Diagnostic Image Analysis Group (DIAG) and Department of Pathology of the Radboud University Medical Center (Radboudumc) in Nijmegen, The Netherlands.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The goal of this challenge is to evaluate new and existing algorithms for automated detection and classification of breast cancer metastases in whole-slide images of histological lymph node sections. This task has high clinical relevance and would normally require extensive microscopic assessment by pathologists. The presence of metastases in lymph nodes has therapeutic implications for breast cancer patients. Therefore, an automated solution would hold great promise to reduce the workload of pathologists while at the same time reduce the subjectivity in diagnosis.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>
&lt;figure id="figure-detection-of-breast-cancer-metastases-in-lymph-nodes">
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="Detection of breast cancer metastases in lymph nodes." srcset="
/project/camelyon/featured_hubada0ba51fa091eb34b957ad6af373e8_629988_7328f63abb61955f723e9608130ba948.webp 400w,
/project/camelyon/featured_hubada0ba51fa091eb34b957ad6af373e8_629988_03ef2794f5f197698bfbb938e54e7a90.webp 760w,
/project/camelyon/featured_hubada0ba51fa091eb34b957ad6af373e8_629988_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w"
src="https://geertlitjens.nl/project/camelyon/featured_hubada0ba51fa091eb34b957ad6af373e8_629988_7328f63abb61955f723e9608130ba948.webp"
width="500"
height="500"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;figcaption>
Detection of breast cancer metastases in lymph nodes.
&lt;/figcaption>&lt;/figure>
&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="task">Task&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The TNM system is an internationally accepted means to classify the extent of cancer spread in patients with a solid tumour. It is one of the most important tools for clinicians to help them select a suitable treatment option and to obtain an indication of prognosis. Since the histological assessment of lymph node metastases is an essential part of TNM classification, CAMELYON17 will focus on the pathologic N-stage, in short: pN-stage.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In clinical practice several lymph nodes are surgically removed after which these nodes are processed in the pathology laboratory. In this challenge we forged &lt;strong>artificial patients&lt;/strong>, with 5 slides provided for each patient where each slide corresponds to exactly one lymph node.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The task in this challenge is to &lt;strong>determine a pN-stage for every patient in the test dataset&lt;/strong>. To compose a pN-stage, the number of positive lymph nodes (i.e. nodes with a metastasis) are counted. For the evaluation of the results we use five class quadratic weighted kappa where the classes are the pN-stages.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="website">Website&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Further information, registration, and the results are available on the &lt;a href="https://camelyon17.grand-challenge.org" target="_blank" rel="noopener">challenge website&lt;/a>.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Deep PCa</title><link>https://geertlitjens.nl/project/deeppca/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://geertlitjens.nl/project/deeppca/</guid><description>&lt;p>Most men die with, not because of prostate cancer. This high incidence-to-mortality ratio sounds like a positive trait, but comes with its own share of problems: high risk of overdiagnosis and overtreatment with significant patient morbidity. To combat overtreatment, several models have been developed to assign patients to risk categories with differing treatment regimes. Although these models show good correlation with patient outcome on the group level, their benefit for the individual patient remains limited.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure id="figure-prostate-cancer-segmentation-using-convolutional-neural-networks">
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="Prostate cancer segmentation using convolutional neural networks." srcset="
/project/deeppca/featured_hu3f41f061ac44526ef00b786c7b376de1_58615_c39d617c39701127e2c5b6f0463b1764.webp 400w,
/project/deeppca/featured_hu3f41f061ac44526ef00b786c7b376de1_58615_4d30aa8e8b7e730f03fb991419b2c68b.webp 760w,
/project/deeppca/featured_hu3f41f061ac44526ef00b786c7b376de1_58615_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w"
src="https://geertlitjens.nl/project/deeppca/featured_hu3f41f061ac44526ef00b786c7b376de1_58615_c39d617c39701127e2c5b6f0463b1764.webp"
width="50%"
height="500"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;figcaption>
Prostate cancer segmentation using convolutional neural networks.
&lt;/figcaption>&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Several groups have shown that quantifying the tumour and its micro-environment at the cellular level can result in biomarkers with strong prognostic potential, for example tumour/stroma ratio, the presence and composition of immune infiltrates or the amount of proliferating (Ki67-positive) cells. However, these findings have not translated to clinical practice due to the cumbersome and subjective manual extraction of these biomarkers from tissue slides.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Recent years have seen the more widespread introduction of whole-slide imaging systems, which for the first time allow computerized processing of tissue slides. Automated extraction of aforementioned quantitative biomarkers through image analysis can achieve the required accuracy and robustness to impact clinical practice. In tandem with these developments, computer vision has seen a machine learning revolution over the past decade due to the advent of deep learning.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In this project, we will combine deep learning and digitized whole-slide imaging of prostate cancer for reproducible extraction of quantitative biomarkers. Furthermore, due to the ability of deep learning systems to learn relevant features without human intervention, we expect to identify novel biomarkers which allow us to further improve the current risk models.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The aim of this project is to prevent unnecessary surgery and adjuvant therapy for individual patients by improving currently established risk models. Risk models will be enhanced through the addition of pre- and post-operative quantitative biomarkers obtained via image analysis and deep learning. We will focus both on the accurate and objective quantification of biomarkers already identified in literature and the discovery of novel biomarkers.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>DeepDerma</title><link>https://geertlitjens.nl/project/deepderma/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://geertlitjens.nl/project/deepderma/</guid><description>&lt;p>Due to the tripling of skin cancer incidence over the past two decades, more skin biopsies and resections are performed than ever before. This has led to an enormous increase in workload for pathologists, who perform the microscopic diagnostics of skin samples.
Most of microscopic skin analysis is not professionally challenging, but it is time consuming and can lead to reduced time for more complex diagnostics and increased wait time for patients. Machine learning and specifically deep learning offers a path to automating the diagnoses of skin samples, which would reduce the pressure on pathologists and the cost of diagnosis, both in time and money.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure id="figure-annotation-of-a-basal-cell-carcinoma-a-skin-cancer-with-typically-good-prognosis">
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="Annotation of a Basal Cell Carcinoma, a skin cancer with, typically, good prognosis." srcset="
/project/deepderma/featured_huab03e89e8b7ea695843dd8e7fc56edc8_571530_1d607c63ae43719b7dba94a2e3b8b364.webp 400w,
/project/deepderma/featured_huab03e89e8b7ea695843dd8e7fc56edc8_571530_ae20c5f4969135c3fd13782c51c3ffe7.webp 760w,
/project/deepderma/featured_huab03e89e8b7ea695843dd8e7fc56edc8_571530_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w"
src="https://geertlitjens.nl/project/deepderma/featured_huab03e89e8b7ea695843dd8e7fc56edc8_571530_1d607c63ae43719b7dba94a2e3b8b364.webp"
width="50%"
height="500"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;figcaption>
Annotation of a Basal Cell Carcinoma, a skin cancer with, typically, good prognosis.
&lt;/figcaption>&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>We propose not just to develop an algorithm which can perform skin diagnostics at the level of an expert pathologist, but also explicitly identify the most fruitful way of integrating these algorithms into the routine workflow. This project is exceedingly timely, as by the end of 2019 all histopathological diagnostics in the Radboud University Medical Center will be done digitally.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The project consists of four work packages. In work package 1, we will collect a large retrospective cohort of annotated and labeled skin biopsies and resections from multiple centers. The focus of work package 2 is on development of algorithms for segmentation of different skin tissue classes, subtyping of basal cell carcinoma, and identification of rare incidental findings. Work package 3 and 4 cover the development and prospective evaluation of the optimal algorithm-integrated workflow in a real world clinical setting.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>After completion, we will have the world’s first prospectively evaluated algorithm-supported workflow for digital pathology, and a valuable, expert labeled, retrospective dataset of skin specimens; both excellent targets for valorization. Last, it will increase the time of pathologists for complex diagnostics and reduce the wait time for patients.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>