<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Projects | Geert Litjens</title><link>https://geertlitjens.nl/project/</link><atom:link href="https://geertlitjens.nl/project/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>Projects</description><generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2019</copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 11 Jan 2022 15:32:00 +0100</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://geertlitjens.nl/media/icon_hue0c2058e8f722cf54419e3dfd4f45926_15543_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url><title>Projects</title><link>https://geertlitjens.nl/project/</link></image><item><title>PANCAIM</title><link>https://geertlitjens.nl/project/eu-pancaim/</link><pubDate>Tue, 11 Jan 2022 15:32:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://geertlitjens.nl/project/eu-pancaim/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="overview">Overview&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The central PANCAIM concept is to successfully exploit available genomic and clinical data to improve personalized medicine of pancreatic cancer. PANCAIM’s concept is unique as it integrates the whole spectrum of genomics with radiomics and pathomics, the three future pillars of personalized medicine. The integration of these three modalities is very challenging in the clinic, but also with AI. PANCAIM uses an explainable, data-efficient, two-staged AI approach. AI biomarkers transform the unimodal data domains into interpretable likelihoods of intermediate disease features. A second AI
layer merges the biomarkers and responds with an integrated assessment of prognosis, prediction and monitoring of therapy response, to assist in clinical decision making.
PANCAIM builds on four key concepts of AI in Healthcare: data providers, clinical expertise, AI developers, and MedTech companies to connect to data and bring AI to healthcare. Data quantity and quality is the main factor for successful AI. Partners provide eleven Pan European repositories of almost 6000 patients that are open to ongoing accrual. SME Collective Minds builds the GDPR data platform that hosts the data and provides a trustable connection to healthcare for even more and sustainable data. SME TheHyve builds tooling to connect to more genomic repositories (EOSC Health). Six
Pan European academic centers provide clinical expertise across all modalities and help realize a curated, high quality annotated data set. Partners also include expert AI healthcare researchers across all clinical modalities with a proven track record. Finally, Siemens Healthineers provides their AI expertise and tooling to bring AI into healthcare for clinical validation and swift clinical integration in 3000 health care institutes.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>
&lt;figure id="figure-integration-of-ct-and-pathology">
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="Integration of CT and pathology" srcset="
/project/eu-pancaim/featured_huc33219bb2767acfe72c5a387084a2658_379429_8297772df108dec26ee750096995be04.webp 400w,
/project/eu-pancaim/featured_huc33219bb2767acfe72c5a387084a2658_379429_dadfd14345de9a5c898338f0c6bec109.webp 760w,
/project/eu-pancaim/featured_huc33219bb2767acfe72c5a387084a2658_379429_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w"
src="https://geertlitjens.nl/project/eu-pancaim/featured_huc33219bb2767acfe72c5a387084a2658_379429_8297772df108dec26ee750096995be04.webp"
width="480"
height="361"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;figcaption>
Integration of CT and pathology
&lt;/figcaption>&lt;/figure>
&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="tasks">Tasks&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Pathology is a diagnostic gold standard for PDAC. However, the information it provides is limited to definitive confirmation of the diagnostic entity and the size and locoregional extent of the tumour. The only tumour-intrinsic feature is the grade of differentiation, a historical concept that is of no relevance for the management of PDAC. The rich information contained in tumour morphology integrates results of interactions at all levels - genetic, epigenetic, microenvironmental -, but is left totally unexplored. It is only with the advent of AI that attempts at deciphering this rich information have been undertaken. Recent studies on a variety of other cancers show that AI can extract information from routine pathology tissue sections that relate to underlying genomic aberrations and allows prognostic discrimination between patients that are currently lumped within the same clinical stage. With the wealth of data accessible in its repository, PANCAIM is in a unique position to decipher and fully exploit the prognostic and predictive information that hitherto has remained unmined in surgical and biopsy specimens from PDAC patients.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Recent studies on a variety of other cancers show that AI can extract information from routine pathology tissue sections that relates to underlying genomic aberrations and allows prognostic discrimination between patients that are currently lumped within the same clinical stage. Although this has been shown and applied in for example, breast cancer [Jaber et al, Breast Cancer Research, 2020] and mesothelioma [Courtiol et al, Nature Medicine 2019], these insights have not yet been applied to PDAC. A key reason is the limited availability of large datasets that combine radiology, pathology, genetics, and clinical follow-up. With the wealth of data accessible in its repository, PANCAIM is in a unique position to decipher and fully exploit the prognostic and predictive information that hitherto has remained unmined in surgical and biopsy specimens from PDAC patients. Specifically, it is our ambition to use novel machine learning techniques such as neural image compression [Tellez et al, TPAMI 2019] to elucidate key pathomics features which can help predict prognosis, treatment response and genetic alterations in PDAC (Figure 9, Figure 8). By additionally applying for the latest advances in explainable artificial intelligence, such as attention-weighting and saliency mapping, PANCAIM furthers the acceptance and integration of these pathomic features in clinical practice.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>IMI BigPicture</title><link>https://geertlitjens.nl/project/imi-bigpicture/</link><pubDate>Tue, 11 Jan 2022 15:31:52 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://geertlitjens.nl/project/imi-bigpicture/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="overview">Overview&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>BIGPICTURE, a pathology-led consortium, has the vision to become the catalyst in digital transformation in Pathology. Our
mission is to create the first European GDPR compliant platform, in which both quality-controlled Whole Slide Imaging (WSI)
data and advanced Artificial intelligence (AI) algorithms will exist. The BIGPICTURE platform will be built on existing assets
of ELIXIR EU data infrastructure, including the federated European Genome-phenome Archive (EGA) technology for
managing the exchange of confidential information between contributors and users. The consortium will use Cytomine, an
established open-source, cross-platform framework to develop unique tools for access to WSI, including annotations and
visualisation of algorithm results, while we will develop new and generic models to facilitate AI development and mining of
WSI data. By engaging and building consensus with all the relevant stakeholders, we will contribute to the development of a
regulatory framework for digital slides and AI-based methods. Finally, BIGPICTURE envisions sustainability of its platform
through a community- based model which relies on reciprocity, value creation and inclusiveness.
To achieve our vision, we have brought together Europe’s leaders in the field of computational pathology who have access
to national and European high-performance computing infrastructures as well as Europe’s fully digitalised pathology
departments. Additionally, the consortium has currently access to approximately 4.5 million clinical WSI covering a wider
range of indications through 17 partners and 23 third parties from the largest European and international pathology and trial
groups. Our consortium is further strengthened by the presence of the European Society of Pathology, Digital Pathology
Association, FDA and 9 SMEs as partners, while we are further supported by professional societies, and patient advocates.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>ICARUS</title><link>https://geertlitjens.nl/project/vidi-icarus/</link><pubDate>Tue, 11 Jan 2022 15:29:56 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://geertlitjens.nl/project/vidi-icarus/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="overview">Overview&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>An ever-increasing amount of treatment options is available to prostate cancer patients. Although this is a positive development, it also increases the complexity of selecting the right therapy for the individual patient. The fusion of in and ex vivo information streams, such as from radiology and pathology, offers a promising avenue for improved models of disease physiology and progression, and consequently, better strategies for treatment selection. However, to build accurate models, large sets of fused radiology/pathology data are needed, which have been impossible to obtain due to the time-consuming and expensive nature of acquiring such datasets.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In this project, we propose an artificial-intelligence-based platform that can automatically combine large archival sets of digitized histopathological slides and multi-parametric MRI (mp-MRI) and leverage them to build a disease model which will improve 1) identification of clinically significant prostate cancer, 2) selection of patients for active surveillance, and 3) predict lutetium-PSMA treatment success.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>
&lt;figure id="figure-flowchart-of-the-interlocking-work-packages">
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="Flowchart of the interlocking work packages" srcset="
/project/vidi-icarus/featured_hu870ad888f693946160ad12cf0c6727a2_242380_235c226354bd2c55292402cf8a4cd756.webp 400w,
/project/vidi-icarus/featured_hu870ad888f693946160ad12cf0c6727a2_242380_ef114b7c9d66fbbee389f510f5a1db6b.webp 760w,
/project/vidi-icarus/featured_hu870ad888f693946160ad12cf0c6727a2_242380_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w"
src="https://geertlitjens.nl/project/vidi-icarus/featured_hu870ad888f693946160ad12cf0c6727a2_242380_235c226354bd2c55292402cf8a4cd756.webp"
width="760"
height="618"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;figcaption>
Flowchart of the interlocking work packages
&lt;/figcaption>&lt;/figure>
&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="tasks">Tasks&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>This project encompasses five objectives: I) establish a collection of combined mp-MRI and digitized prostatectomy specimens from 1350 patients, II) build an automated reconstruction algorithm for the generation of 3D tissue volumes from 2D digitized histopathology slides, III) develop registration techniques for spatial alignment of ex vivo histopathology to in vivo mp-MRI, IV) learn mp-MRI / histopathology correlations using unique deep streaming generative models, and V) Evaluate the learned correlations for improved diagnostics, active surveillance, and lutetium-PSMA treatment selection.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The impact of the project will not just be improved diagnostic and treatment decisions for patients but can be the starting point of an entirely new field of cross-medical-specialty research; the developed platform can be leveraged for other cancer types and even non-oncological diseases.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>AISCAP</title><link>https://geertlitjens.nl/project/erc-aiscap/</link><pubDate>Tue, 11 Jan 2022 15:29:38 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://geertlitjens.nl/project/erc-aiscap/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="overview">Overview&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Computational pathology, the application of advanced machine learning (ML) methods to digitized tissue sections, can revolutionize cancer care and research. Specifically, I propose a paradigm shift by moving away from the currently used manual grading systems towards ML-supported patient prognostication. However, significant knowledge gaps are hindering the field of computational pathology. We do not know how to: 1) effectively leverage global and local information in WSIs, 2) identify pan-cancer and cancer-specific prognostic features, and 3) make ML models explainable and interpretable.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>
&lt;figure id="figure-flowchart-of-the-interlocking-work-packages">
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="Flowchart of the interlocking work packages" srcset="
/project/erc-aiscap/featured_hua9c1074d7efe068f74d45a2f6193ecd8_184892_956574a2efb802c9a8e60a7c864f7944.webp 400w,
/project/erc-aiscap/featured_hua9c1074d7efe068f74d45a2f6193ecd8_184892_633411acd04525656c0bd27e3ed63564.webp 760w,
/project/erc-aiscap/featured_hua9c1074d7efe068f74d45a2f6193ecd8_184892_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w"
src="https://geertlitjens.nl/project/erc-aiscap/featured_hua9c1074d7efe068f74d45a2f6193ecd8_184892_956574a2efb802c9a8e60a7c864f7944.webp"
width="760"
height="488"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;figcaption>
Flowchart of the interlocking work packages
&lt;/figcaption>&lt;/figure>
&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="tasks">Tasks&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>This ambitious project will address these critical knowledge gaps by building on the novel stochastic streaming gradient descent developed in my group. First, I will push SSGD to the next level by integrating hierarchical hyperparameter optimization and separable convolutions. Second, to identify pan-cancer and cancer-specific prognostic biomarkers, I will integrate innovative multi-task and cross-task learning algorithms with SSGD. Third, I will leverage the latest advances in concept learning and natural language processing to endow deep neural networks with unprecedented transparency and explainability. Last, I will validate our developed methodology in the largest dataset of oncological WSIs globally.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>By publicly releasing all developed tools and data, the proposed project will have a scientific multiplier effect on the fields of computational pathology, machine learning, and oncology. Specifically, the enhanced SSGD method can open new research areas for ML that require data across scales, such as remote sensing. My novel approach to ML explainability can encourage the adoption of innovative technologies, such as self-driving cars. Last, the derived specific and pan-cancer biomarkers will have a tremendous impact on the quest to understand cancer development and progression, and ultimately on public health and the economy&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>DeepGrading</title><link>https://geertlitjens.nl/project/ppp-deepgrading/</link><pubDate>Tue, 11 Jan 2022 15:29:21 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://geertlitjens.nl/project/ppp-deepgrading/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="overview">Overview&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Optimal treatment decisions for cancer patients are hampered by variability in grading among pathologists. When there is a suspicion for cancer, typically a tissue biopsy is taken. This biopsy is stained with hematoxylin and eosin (H&amp;amp;E) and evaluated by a pathologist for the presence and aggressiveness (i.e. grading) of the tumor. Professional organizations have drafted standardized guidelines on how this grading should be performed; however, there is still significant inter- and intra-observer variation among pathologists. Artificial intelligence, specifically through deep learning, has shown to increase efficiency and consistency in histopathological diagnosis, and, recently, to perform grading at the expert level. We have prototypes of such algorithms validated in the lab which could significantly impact clinical practice, but have not yet been tested in routine diagnostics. The aim of this project is three-fold.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>
&lt;figure id="figure-example-of-automated-prostate-cancer-grading-including-bar-plots-of-grades-assigned-by-multiple-pathologists">
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="Example of automated prostate cancer grading, including bar plots of grades assigned by multiple pathologists" srcset="
/project/ppp-deepgrading/featured_hu89bde7ffdd6d32f799a92da8cbce97e7_165693_8d2064006c7afc74e65315ac2b5f696a.webp 400w,
/project/ppp-deepgrading/featured_hu89bde7ffdd6d32f799a92da8cbce97e7_165693_ae810ec51e0d1ebb380abef5920253ac.webp 760w,
/project/ppp-deepgrading/featured_hu89bde7ffdd6d32f799a92da8cbce97e7_165693_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w"
src="https://geertlitjens.nl/project/ppp-deepgrading/featured_hu89bde7ffdd6d32f799a92da8cbce97e7_165693_8d2064006c7afc74e65315ac2b5f696a.webp"
width="760"
height="376"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;figcaption>
Example of automated prostate cancer grading, including bar plots of grades assigned by multiple pathologists
&lt;/figcaption>&lt;/figure>
&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="tasks">Tasks&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>First, we will further develop our existing grading algorithms for prostate and breast cancer, to enhance robustness to variance in data sources and disease (sub)types. Second, we will conduct studies to determine the most efficient way to integrate algorithms into the routine workflow. Last, we will evaluate the most promising workflow prospectively in pilot lines at both peripheral and academic centers to assess performance. Currently, there are no algorithms commercially available which can do pathologist-level grading of cancer. Thus, this project can have both significant societal and economic impact. From a societal perspective, we can make expert grading available at locations without access to subspecialized pathologists. Outside the Netherlands, there are pathologist shortages in countries such as India and China where these algorithms could have even more impact. Thirona is already ISO13485 certified and has experience with CE certification and FDA 510(k) clearance. As such, upon completion of this project, algorithms could be commercially available quickly, offering the potential for a significant disruption of the health care market.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>
&lt;figure id="figure-examples-of-prostate-biopsy-transurethral-resection-and-prostatectomy">
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="Examples of prostate biopsy, transurethral resection, and prostatectomy" srcset="
/project/ppp-deepgrading/surgical_entities_hu7557648230985fa00b2bf2b28982a3d2_347217_4d8fcd77f163e543bc103b6be72a9316.webp 400w,
/project/ppp-deepgrading/surgical_entities_hu7557648230985fa00b2bf2b28982a3d2_347217_44de861b65b54ee2e4ad3bc38931da22.webp 760w,
/project/ppp-deepgrading/surgical_entities_hu7557648230985fa00b2bf2b28982a3d2_347217_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w"
src="https://geertlitjens.nl/project/ppp-deepgrading/surgical_entities_hu7557648230985fa00b2bf2b28982a3d2_347217_4d8fcd77f163e543bc103b6be72a9316.webp"
width="760"
height="248"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;figcaption>
Examples of prostate biopsy, transurethral resection, and prostatectomy
&lt;/figcaption>&lt;/figure>
&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Automated Analysis of Histopathological Clinical Trial Data</title><link>https://geertlitjens.nl/project/aahctd/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Apr 2015 12:16:34 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://geertlitjens.nl/project/aahctd/</guid><description>&lt;p>To accuractely determine the outcome of clinical trials careful analysis of the biomarkers is required. In recent years this has become more and more complex due to quantity of biomarkers that has to be assessed in new clinical trials. Furthermore, as we move to more personalized therapy, we need to be able to measure even subtle changes in biomarker expression, putting a larger emphasis on accurate and precise biomarker quantification. These changes have made manual assessment of biomarker expression tedious, time-consuming, and, often, inaccurate.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure id="figure-quantification-of-cd3-positive-cells-inside-yellow-and-outside-green-the-invasive-margin-of-prostate-cancer-orange-specimens">
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="Quantification of CD3-positive cells inside (yellow) and outside (green) the invasive margin of prostate cancer (orange) specimens." srcset="
/project/aahctd/featured_hu8dea62950b20b086faff196c1d701874_176128_b9d45b7c0672b0f780191e26c3615847.webp 400w,
/project/aahctd/featured_hu8dea62950b20b086faff196c1d701874_176128_9cf9f7d9074c024bb7cc885154553a61.webp 760w,
/project/aahctd/featured_hu8dea62950b20b086faff196c1d701874_176128_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w"
src="https://geertlitjens.nl/project/aahctd/featured_hu8dea62950b20b086faff196c1d701874_176128_b9d45b7c0672b0f780191e26c3615847.webp"
width="50%"
height="484"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;figcaption>
Quantification of CD3-positive cells inside (yellow) and outside (green) the invasive margin of prostate cancer (orange) specimens.
&lt;/figcaption>&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Within this project, funded by the &lt;a href="https://www.humboldt-foundation.de/web/home.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Humboldt Foundation&lt;/a>, we set out to develop machine learning tools to automate the quantification and discovery of biomarkers in a variety of clinical trials. Specifically, we looked at applications in prostate cancer immunotherapy, lung cancer prognosis, and MAGE-expression in head and neck cancers.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>ASAP</title><link>https://geertlitjens.nl/project/asap/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2014 12:25:34 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://geertlitjens.nl/project/asap/</guid><description>&lt;p>ASAP (Automated Slide Analysis Platform) was developed by the Computation Pathology Group, part of the Diagnostic Image Analysis Group, at the Radboud University Medical Center. It was started after frustration with the current freely available software for annotating multi-resolution digital pathology images. For more details head to the project site.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Computerized Detection of Prostate Cancer in Multi-Parametric MRI</title><link>https://geertlitjens.nl/project/mpmri-pca/</link><pubDate>Thu, 07 Jan 2010 11:55:45 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://geertlitjens.nl/project/mpmri-pca/</guid><description>&lt;p>Prostate cancer is the most commonly diagnosed malignancy and the second leading cause of cancer death among men in the Netherlands. Due to the shortcomings of the current diagnostic pathway for prostate cancer, especially with respect to assessing cancer aggressiveness, alternative strategies are being investigated. Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) has emerged as an important modality to assist and potentially replace (part of) the current diagnostic pathway. The high complexity of prostate MRI and the lack of sufficient expertise among the radiological community at large has opened the door for (semi-)automated analysis of prostate MRI by computer systems, with or without human intervention.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure id="figure-transversal-slide-through-the-prosate-in-a-t2-weighted-mri-sequence">
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="Transversal slide through the prosate in a T2-weighted MRI sequence." srcset="
/project/mpmri-pca/featured_hu82c705709ed6cbe2deb511e0b8d9074a_253218_2b4c3d61f6cf40e2e403ae0e13e40869.webp 400w,
/project/mpmri-pca/featured_hu82c705709ed6cbe2deb511e0b8d9074a_253218_d4b4077858c208b27c05cd8b85eabe35.webp 760w,
/project/mpmri-pca/featured_hu82c705709ed6cbe2deb511e0b8d9074a_253218_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w"
src="https://geertlitjens.nl/project/mpmri-pca/featured_hu82c705709ed6cbe2deb511e0b8d9074a_253218_2b4c3d61f6cf40e2e403ae0e13e40869.webp"
width="50%"
height="545"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;figcaption>
Transversal slide through the prosate in a T2-weighted MRI sequence.
&lt;/figcaption>&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Within this project such as system was developed and evaluated. It consisted of several key components: segmentation of the prostate gland in MRI, discovering cancer-specific features, system development and evaluation. The results were reported through a number of publications which are listed below and summarized in my &lt;a href="https://geertlitjens.nl/publication/litj-15-a/">PhD Thesis&lt;/a>.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>CAMELYON</title><link>https://geertlitjens.nl/project/camelyon/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://geertlitjens.nl/project/camelyon/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="overview">Overview&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Built on the success of its predecessor, CAMELYON17 is the second grand challenge in pathology organised by the Diagnostic Image Analysis Group (DIAG) and Department of Pathology of the Radboud University Medical Center (Radboudumc) in Nijmegen, The Netherlands.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The goal of this challenge is to evaluate new and existing algorithms for automated detection and classification of breast cancer metastases in whole-slide images of histological lymph node sections. This task has high clinical relevance and would normally require extensive microscopic assessment by pathologists. The presence of metastases in lymph nodes has therapeutic implications for breast cancer patients. Therefore, an automated solution would hold great promise to reduce the workload of pathologists while at the same time reduce the subjectivity in diagnosis.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>
&lt;figure id="figure-detection-of-breast-cancer-metastases-in-lymph-nodes">
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="Detection of breast cancer metastases in lymph nodes." srcset="
/project/camelyon/featured_hubada0ba51fa091eb34b957ad6af373e8_629988_7328f63abb61955f723e9608130ba948.webp 400w,
/project/camelyon/featured_hubada0ba51fa091eb34b957ad6af373e8_629988_03ef2794f5f197698bfbb938e54e7a90.webp 760w,
/project/camelyon/featured_hubada0ba51fa091eb34b957ad6af373e8_629988_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w"
src="https://geertlitjens.nl/project/camelyon/featured_hubada0ba51fa091eb34b957ad6af373e8_629988_7328f63abb61955f723e9608130ba948.webp"
width="500"
height="500"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;figcaption>
Detection of breast cancer metastases in lymph nodes.
&lt;/figcaption>&lt;/figure>
&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="task">Task&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The TNM system is an internationally accepted means to classify the extent of cancer spread in patients with a solid tumour. It is one of the most important tools for clinicians to help them select a suitable treatment option and to obtain an indication of prognosis. Since the histological assessment of lymph node metastases is an essential part of TNM classification, CAMELYON17 will focus on the pathologic N-stage, in short: pN-stage.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In clinical practice several lymph nodes are surgically removed after which these nodes are processed in the pathology laboratory. In this challenge we forged &lt;strong>artificial patients&lt;/strong>, with 5 slides provided for each patient where each slide corresponds to exactly one lymph node.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The task in this challenge is to &lt;strong>determine a pN-stage for every patient in the test dataset&lt;/strong>. To compose a pN-stage, the number of positive lymph nodes (i.e. nodes with a metastasis) are counted. For the evaluation of the results we use five class quadratic weighted kappa where the classes are the pN-stages.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="website">Website&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Further information, registration, and the results are available on the &lt;a href="https://camelyon17.grand-challenge.org" target="_blank" rel="noopener">challenge website&lt;/a>.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Deep PCa</title><link>https://geertlitjens.nl/project/deeppca/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://geertlitjens.nl/project/deeppca/</guid><description>&lt;p>Most men die with, not because of prostate cancer. This high incidence-to-mortality ratio sounds like a positive trait, but comes with its own share of problems: high risk of overdiagnosis and overtreatment with significant patient morbidity. To combat overtreatment, several models have been developed to assign patients to risk categories with differing treatment regimes. Although these models show good correlation with patient outcome on the group level, their benefit for the individual patient remains limited.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure id="figure-prostate-cancer-segmentation-using-convolutional-neural-networks">
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="Prostate cancer segmentation using convolutional neural networks." srcset="
/project/deeppca/featured_hu3f41f061ac44526ef00b786c7b376de1_58615_c39d617c39701127e2c5b6f0463b1764.webp 400w,
/project/deeppca/featured_hu3f41f061ac44526ef00b786c7b376de1_58615_4d30aa8e8b7e730f03fb991419b2c68b.webp 760w,
/project/deeppca/featured_hu3f41f061ac44526ef00b786c7b376de1_58615_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w"
src="https://geertlitjens.nl/project/deeppca/featured_hu3f41f061ac44526ef00b786c7b376de1_58615_c39d617c39701127e2c5b6f0463b1764.webp"
width="50%"
height="500"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;figcaption>
Prostate cancer segmentation using convolutional neural networks.
&lt;/figcaption>&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Several groups have shown that quantifying the tumour and its micro-environment at the cellular level can result in biomarkers with strong prognostic potential, for example tumour/stroma ratio, the presence and composition of immune infiltrates or the amount of proliferating (Ki67-positive) cells. However, these findings have not translated to clinical practice due to the cumbersome and subjective manual extraction of these biomarkers from tissue slides.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Recent years have seen the more widespread introduction of whole-slide imaging systems, which for the first time allow computerized processing of tissue slides. Automated extraction of aforementioned quantitative biomarkers through image analysis can achieve the required accuracy and robustness to impact clinical practice. In tandem with these developments, computer vision has seen a machine learning revolution over the past decade due to the advent of deep learning.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In this project, we will combine deep learning and digitized whole-slide imaging of prostate cancer for reproducible extraction of quantitative biomarkers. Furthermore, due to the ability of deep learning systems to learn relevant features without human intervention, we expect to identify novel biomarkers which allow us to further improve the current risk models.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The aim of this project is to prevent unnecessary surgery and adjuvant therapy for individual patients by improving currently established risk models. Risk models will be enhanced through the addition of pre- and post-operative quantitative biomarkers obtained via image analysis and deep learning. We will focus both on the accurate and objective quantification of biomarkers already identified in literature and the discovery of novel biomarkers.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>DeepDerma</title><link>https://geertlitjens.nl/project/deepderma/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://geertlitjens.nl/project/deepderma/</guid><description>&lt;p>Due to the tripling of skin cancer incidence over the past two decades, more skin biopsies and resections are performed than ever before. This has led to an enormous increase in workload for pathologists, who perform the microscopic diagnostics of skin samples.
Most of microscopic skin analysis is not professionally challenging, but it is time consuming and can lead to reduced time for more complex diagnostics and increased wait time for patients. Machine learning and specifically deep learning offers a path to automating the diagnoses of skin samples, which would reduce the pressure on pathologists and the cost of diagnosis, both in time and money.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure id="figure-annotation-of-a-basal-cell-carcinoma-a-skin-cancer-with-typically-good-prognosis">
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="Annotation of a Basal Cell Carcinoma, a skin cancer with, typically, good prognosis." srcset="
/project/deepderma/featured_huab03e89e8b7ea695843dd8e7fc56edc8_571530_1d607c63ae43719b7dba94a2e3b8b364.webp 400w,
/project/deepderma/featured_huab03e89e8b7ea695843dd8e7fc56edc8_571530_ae20c5f4969135c3fd13782c51c3ffe7.webp 760w,
/project/deepderma/featured_huab03e89e8b7ea695843dd8e7fc56edc8_571530_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w"
src="https://geertlitjens.nl/project/deepderma/featured_huab03e89e8b7ea695843dd8e7fc56edc8_571530_1d607c63ae43719b7dba94a2e3b8b364.webp"
width="50%"
height="500"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;figcaption>
Annotation of a Basal Cell Carcinoma, a skin cancer with, typically, good prognosis.
&lt;/figcaption>&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>We propose not just to develop an algorithm which can perform skin diagnostics at the level of an expert pathologist, but also explicitly identify the most fruitful way of integrating these algorithms into the routine workflow. This project is exceedingly timely, as by the end of 2019 all histopathological diagnostics in the Radboud University Medical Center will be done digitally.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The project consists of four work packages. In work package 1, we will collect a large retrospective cohort of annotated and labeled skin biopsies and resections from multiple centers. The focus of work package 2 is on development of algorithms for segmentation of different skin tissue classes, subtyping of basal cell carcinoma, and identification of rare incidental findings. Work package 3 and 4 cover the development and prospective evaluation of the optimal algorithm-integrated workflow in a real world clinical setting.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>After completion, we will have the world’s first prospectively evaluated algorithm-supported workflow for digital pathology, and a valuable, expert labeled, retrospective dataset of skin specimens; both excellent targets for valorization. Last, it will increase the time of pathologists for complex diagnostics and reduce the wait time for patients.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>