<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>IMI | Geert Litjens</title><link>https://geertlitjens.nl/tag/imi/</link><atom:link href="https://geertlitjens.nl/tag/imi/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>IMI</description><generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2019</copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 11 Jan 2022 15:31:52 +0100</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://geertlitjens.nl/media/icon_hue0c2058e8f722cf54419e3dfd4f45926_15543_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url><title>IMI</title><link>https://geertlitjens.nl/tag/imi/</link></image><item><title>IMI BigPicture</title><link>https://geertlitjens.nl/project/imi-bigpicture/</link><pubDate>Tue, 11 Jan 2022 15:31:52 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://geertlitjens.nl/project/imi-bigpicture/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="overview">Overview&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>BIGPICTURE, a pathology-led consortium, has the vision to become the catalyst in digital transformation in Pathology. Our
mission is to create the first European GDPR compliant platform, in which both quality-controlled Whole Slide Imaging (WSI)
data and advanced Artificial intelligence (AI) algorithms will exist. The BIGPICTURE platform will be built on existing assets
of ELIXIR EU data infrastructure, including the federated European Genome-phenome Archive (EGA) technology for
managing the exchange of confidential information between contributors and users. The consortium will use Cytomine, an
established open-source, cross-platform framework to develop unique tools for access to WSI, including annotations and
visualisation of algorithm results, while we will develop new and generic models to facilitate AI development and mining of
WSI data. By engaging and building consensus with all the relevant stakeholders, we will contribute to the development of a
regulatory framework for digital slides and AI-based methods. Finally, BIGPICTURE envisions sustainability of its platform
through a community- based model which relies on reciprocity, value creation and inclusiveness.
To achieve our vision, we have brought together Europe’s leaders in the field of computational pathology who have access
to national and European high-performance computing infrastructures as well as Europe’s fully digitalised pathology
departments. Additionally, the consortium has currently access to approximately 4.5 million clinical WSI covering a wider
range of indications through 17 partners and 23 third parties from the largest European and international pathology and trial
groups. Our consortium is further strengthened by the presence of the European Society of Pathology, Digital Pathology
Association, FDA and 9 SMEs as partners, while we are further supported by professional societies, and patient advocates.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>